A Guide to the Papers of William Faulkner and Family, circa 1898-1997
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of William Faulkner and Family circa 1898-1997
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9817-l
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were loaned to the University of Virginia Library by Jill Faulkner Summers on May 4, 1998.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of William Faulkner, ca. 1898-1997, 1,250 items (6 boxes, ca. 2.5 linear feet) contains manuscripts and proofs; literary correspondence and legal papers; photographs and printed items relating to Faulkner; recordings; daybooks and ledgers; papers relating to Estelle Oldham Faulkner and Jill Faulkner Summers; and a few miscellaneous items.
Manuscripts and proofs include typescripts with autograph revisions of the stories Almost, Snow, With caution and dispatch [photocopy only], Knight's Gambit, [photocopy only], and the play Twixt Cup and Lip; several speeches [photocopies only]; and galley proof of The Reivers and the introduction of Light in August. With these are periodical publications of several Faulkner short stories.
Financial and legal papers include various agreements with Liveright, Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, Warner Brothers, Winchester Pictures, Random House, Harold Ober Associates, Esquire and the University of Mississippi. Correspondents include Albert Erskine, Harold Hayes, and Peter Shepherd.
Miscellaneous items in the collection include two copies of Faulkner's broadside To the voters of Oxford on beer; drawings; personal financial and legal papers; memorabilia; early school reports and an 1897 reader; programs; daybooks, ledgers, and flight logs; and a record of horse breeding.
Audio recordings include a University of Virginia news conference on Faulkner with comments by Fredson Bowers, Floyd Stoval, James B. Colvert, F. W. Bernhauser and John Cook Wyllie and the Faulkner story by the Ford Foundation.
Family papers include correspondence, stories, poems, a painting and a lullaby by Estelle Faulkner, and school programs and honors of Jill Faulkner Summers. The collection also contains manuscripts by Mrs. Phil Stone, Enrique Auvert, Paul D. Summers, Jr. and Malcolm Franklin.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically within series and has six series, including: Series I: Literary Works by William Faulkner (Boxes 1-2), which includes Subseries A: Manuscripts of William Faulkner and Subseries B: Printed Manuscripts of William Faulkner; Series II: Literary Correspondence and Legal Papers concerning William Faulkner's Works (Box 2); Series III: Topical Subjects relating to William Faulkner (Boxes 3-4); Series IV: Photographs and Printed relating to William Faulkner and family (Boxes 4-5); Series V: Papers relating to Estelle Oldham Faulkner and Jill Faulkner (Box 6); and, Series VI: Bound Volumes and Audio Recordings (Box 6)
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Works by William Faulkner
  - Subseries A: Manuscripts of William Faulkner
    - Almost, various pages from a story by William Faulkner, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:1)
      With autograph revisions by author, 10 pages; with cover letter from Dan Brennan (on letterhead of Eric G. Hoyer, Mayor of Minneapolis) in which Brennan returns these pages and a photograph [not present] to [Faulkner?].
    - Bench for Two and Light in August, manuscript pages denied by Faulkner as being his work, n.d., TMs (carbon). (Box-folder 1:2)
      Extremely fragile.
    - Light in August introduction by Richard H. Rovere, n.d., Galley Proof. (Box-folder 1:3)
    - The Reivers, 1962 January 10, Galley Proof. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Printer's proof with notations and revisions.
    - The Reivers, 1962 February 9, Galley Proof. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Printer's proof for first edition with notations and revisions.
    - The Reivers, [1962] (Box-folder 1:6)
    - Rose of Lebanon, short story by William Faulkner, n.d., AMs (copy). (Box-folder 1:7)
      Copy made from original in the University of Virginia Special Collections, 9 pages; with a 14-page transcript.
    - Snow, short story by William Faulkner, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:8)
      With autograph revisions by author, 21 pages; black paper cover entitled Snow by William Faulkner/Harold Ober Associates...
    - Twixt Cup and Lip, play by William Faulkner, n.d., TMs (copy). 22 pages. (Box-folder 1:9)
    - Unpublished Stories by William Faulkner, with autograph revisions by the author, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 1:10)
      Includes Snow, 16 pages; With Caution and Dispatch, two versions 15 pages and 21 pages [photocopies only],; and, Knight's Gambit, 23 pages [photocopy only]. A Courtship, which is listed on the first page, is not present. Black paper cover entitled Unpublished Stories by William Faulkner/Harold Ober...
    - Speeches by William Faulkner (all untitled), [photocopies only] n.d., 4 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Subseries B: Printed Manuscripts by William Faulkner
    - Delta Autumn, story by William Faulkner published in Story, 1942, Printed. 10 pages. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Gold is not Always, story by William Faulkner published in The Atlantic, 1940 November, Printed. (Box-folder 2:2)
      8 pages.
    - Kentucky: May: Saturday/Three Days to the Afternoon, article by William Faulkner in Sports Illustrated, 1955 May, Printed. (Box-folder 2:3)
      5 pages.
    - A Name for the City, story by William Faulkner, published in Harper's Magazine Centennial Issue 1850-1950, 1950 October, Printed. (Box-folder 2:4)
      10 pages.
    - A Rose for Emily and other stories by William Faulkner, 1942, Paperbound Book. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Armed Services Edition with introduction by Saxe Commins.
    - Rose of Lebanon, story by William Faulkner published in The Oxford American, 1995 May/June, Printed. (Box-folder 2:6)
      20 pages; also includes 5 portraits of Faulkner by various artists.
    - Spotted Horses, short story by William Faulkner, published in Scribner's Magazine, 1931 June, Printed. (Box-folder 2:7)
      13 pages.
- Series II: Literary Correspondence and Legal Papers re: William Faulkner's Works
  - Correspondence of William Faulkner, 1944-1961, 9 items. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Correspondence of William Faulkner, 1959, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 2:9)
    Electrostatic copies.
  - Correspondence of William Faulkner, 1962, 10 items. (Box-folder 2:10)
    Includes an unsent letter 1962 Jun. 30, from William Faulkner to "Chere Madame" (Ginette Strickland)
  - Certificates of Registration of Claim to Renewal of Copyright between William Faulkner and Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, Inc. for stories: Ambuscade, Retreat, Raid, and Skirmish at Sartoris.1934-1935, 4 items. (Box-folder 2:11)
    Negative photostats.
  - Memoranda of Agreement between William Faulkner and the Liveright Publishing Corporation, New York, New York, for the dramatization of Soldier's Pay,1937-1938, 3 items. (Box-folder 2:12)
    Cover letter, January 7, 1937, from Morton Goldman, New York, New York.
  - Letter agreement from Warner Bros. Pictures, West Coast Studios, Burbank, California, to William Faulkner, Oxford, Mississippi, taking care of the extension in his leave of absence from the studio, 1945 March, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Agreement between William Faulkner and Random House, Inc., New York, New York, to follow Intruder in the Dust with a certain work of fiction, presently untitled, and a volume of short stories, 1948 July, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Agreement between William Faulkner, Random House, Inc., and Loew's Incorporated, New York, New York, for motion picture rights for Intruder in the Dust; rider attached, 1948 August, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Agreement between William Faulkner and Winchester Pictures Corporation in connection with the motion picture now entitled The Left Hand of God, 1951 February, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:16)
    Confirmation of agreement and cover letter attached.
  - Agreement between William Faulkner and Random House, Inc., collectively, and Fred Zinnemann and Jay/Julien, collectively, for motion picture rights to The Old Man, 1952 November, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Assignment of Copyright for "world-wide 'motion picture and related rights'" for a portion of The Hamlet, under the title of Lizards in Jamshyd's Courtyard; cover letter, March 11, 1960, from Harold Ober Associates, Inc., New York, New York, 1960 March, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Albert Erskine, Random House, Inc., to William Faulkner, relating to proof questions and other literary matters concerning The Hamlet, Sanctuary, and The Reivers, 1962 February, 1 TLS. (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Harold Hayes, Managing Editor, Esquire, New York, New York, to Mrs. Paul D. [Jill Faulkner] Summers, Jr., 1963 March 14, TLS. (Box-folder 2:20)
    Concerns the publication of one of William Faulkner's manuscripts in a special issue on the literary scene in America; copy of Snow attached.
  - Agreement between Jill Faulkner Summers and the University of Mississippi, granting and leasing the property of Rowan Oak, Oxford, to the University to be preserved as a memorial to William Faulkner, 1963 May, 1 item. (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Albert R. Erskine, Random House, Inc., to Mrs. Paul D. [Jill Faulkner] Summers, Jr., 1974 July 1, TLS. (Box-folder 2:22)
    Concerns a Slovak edition of The Wild Palms.
  - Harold Ober Associates to Mrs. Paul D. [Jill Faulkner] Summers, Jr., 1975 January 6, TLS. (Box-folder 2:23)
    Enclosing two copies of an agreement concerning the motion picture rights to Dry September; agreements not present.
  - Peter Shepherd, Harold Ober Associates, to Prof. Donald MacInnis, McIntire Department of Music, University of Virginia, 1975 May 14, TL (carbon). (Box-folder 2:24)
    Authorization for the composition of an opera based on The Bear; carbon sent to Mrs. Paul D. [Jill Faulkner] Summers, Jr.
  - Random House, Inc. to Mrs. Jill Faulkner Summers, 1976 June 23, TLS. (Box-folder 2:25)
    Confirming an agreement to allow Random House to license Franklin Library quality hardcover reprint rights to Absalom, Absalom and The Sound and the Fury; Random House consents to reprint arrangement for five title.
- Series III: Topical Subjects relating to William Faulkner
  - Broadside, To the Voters of Oxford from William Faulkner, Private Citizen, [1950], 2 copies. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Printed as a correction to the paid printed statement of others concerning "beer."
  - Drawings by William Faulkner, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
    3 pen-and-ink sketches with an equestrian theme, 2 copied pages of 6 pen-and-ink drawings depicting cartoon characters from WF's works, pen-and-ink sketch of survey-map from WF's stories (OS Box T-25).
  - Essays re: Faulkner's works: On William Faulkner's 'The Sound and the Fury' by Evelyn Scott, 1929, 1929-1975, 7 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
    3 copies; The Literary Career of William Faulkner: Catalogue of an Exhibition by James B. Meriwether, Spring 1960- 2 copies; Faulkner Meditations: The Wild Palms by Thomas Merton, Summer 1975; Time and Unburdening and the Recollections of the Lamb: The Easter Service in Faulkner's The Sound and the Fury by Thomas Merton, n.d.
  - Faulkner Library, Miscellaneous, 1933-1961, 20 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Insurance [Penn Mutual Life Insurance Company, Continental Casualty Company, The Home Insurance Company, North British & Mercantile Insurance Company, Phoenix Insurance Company], 1936-1939, 41 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Insurance [Penn Mutual Life Insurance Company, Continental Casualty Company, The Home Insurance Company, North British & Mercantile Insurance Company, Phoenix Insurance Company], 1940-1962, 17 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Internal Revenue Service, 1933-1942, 42 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Last Will and Testament and Codicil, 1934, 1951, 3 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Okatoba Hunting and Fishing Club, 1935, 19 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Oxford Property, 1930-1938, 48 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Property Tax receipts, 1928-1952, 16 items. (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: Receipts, bank deposit slips, etc., 1938-1940, 16 items. (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Financial and Legal Papers: State of Mississippi Taxes, 1937-1961, 36 items. (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Honors and Awards [Republique Francaise recognition of WF's Prix Nobel de Littererature, National Institute of Arts and Letters award of gold medal fiction to WF], 1950, 1962, 2 items. (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Identification cards, passports, and ration cards for Estelle (Oldham) and William Faulkner, 1918-1962, 30 items. (Box-folder 3:15)
    Quiet Birdmen Goodfellow card, Farmington Hunt colors and buttons card, cadet pass 1918, operator's license, hunting and fishing license, vaccination certificate, passports, wallets.
  - Memorabilia, 1925-1956, 13 items. (Box-folder 3:16)
    S.S. Republic Menu, Red Cross armband, postcards, Farmington Hunt Club booklet, printed poem- Une Balad Hedes Femmes Perdues by WF, children's drawings.
  - Programs for stage and movie presentations of Faulkner's work, 1921, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 3:17)
    The Marionettes present The Arrival of Kitty, World Premiere of Intruder in the Dust].
  - Royal Air Force, 1918-1919, 10 items. (Box-folder 3:18)
  - School Reading by Grades/Baldwin's Readers First Year, owned by William Falkner, Oxford, Miss., 1905,1897, Printed. (Box-folder 3:19)
  - School Report cards, 1905-1907, 2 items. (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Southern Literary Festival/A Tribute to William Faulkner; Oxford's Second Pilgrimage, 1965 April-May, 10 items. (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Venezuela: Danzas Venezuela honors, 1961 April, ca. 100 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Verdun: Festival of Inauguration of the Crossroad of this Highway of Freedom... 1947, 30 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Verdun: Travel brochures and maps, [1947], 13 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Victoria y Otros Cuentos for Julia de Asensi, owned and signed by William Faulkner, 1905, Printed. (Box-folder 4:4)
- Series IV: Photographs and Printed relating to William Faulkner and Family
  - Photographs of William Faulkner, [1898-1900], 5 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner, [1901-1902], 5 items. (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner (also see OS Box T-25), [1907-1931], 9 items. (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner, [1930s-1940s], 7 items. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner (also see OS Box T-25), [1950s], 18 items. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner (also see OS Box T-25), [1960s], 17 items. (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner, Estelle Oldham, and Jill Faulkner Summers (also see OS Box T-25), [1962, n.d.], 10 items. (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner family and friends, 1947-1965, 22 items. (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner at Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer Studio, 1949, 15 items. (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner's Awards and Dedications, 1955-1965, 16 items. (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Photographs of William Faulkner's Visit to Japan, 1957, 30 items. (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Photographs: Negatives and Slides, n.d., 18 items. (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Printed Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1924-1959, ca. 50 items. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Printed Articles and Newspapers, 1949-1987, ca. 25 items. (Oversize (OS Box T-25).)
  - Printed Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1960-1979, ca. 50 items. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Printed Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1981-1985, ca. 30 items. (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Printed Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1988, ca. 30 items (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Printed Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1989, ca. 20 items. (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Printed Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1990-1997, ca. 15 items. (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Printed: Congressional Record with note of the death of William Faulkner, 1962 July, Printed. (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Printed: The Faulkner Newsletter and Yoknapatawpha Review, 1992, 3 items. (Box-folder 5:9)
- Series V: Papers relating to Estelle Oldham Faulkner and Jill Faulkner
  - A Crossing, story by Estelle Oldham Faulkner, n.d., 2 TMss. (Box-folder 6:1)
    27 pages.
  - Correspondence of Estelle Oldham Faulkner, 1969, n.d., 3 items. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Crayon and watercolor drawings by Tad Summers as a young boy, n.d., 25 items. (Oversize OS Box T-25.)
  - Dr. Wohlenski, story by Estelle Oldham Faulkner, with autograph revisions, n.d., TMs. 33 pages. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - 'Lullaby for Jill'- with all my Heart, lyrics by Estelle Oldham Faulkner; music score by Bowen, McDuff, and Garnett, June 24, n.y., TMs. (Oversize OS Box T-25.)
  - Painting of a little boy, head and upper chest, framed, by Estelle Oldham Faulkner, n.d., 1 item. (Oversize OS Box T-25.)
  - Painting of a little girl, head and shoulders, looking upward, by M Falkner [Murray C. Falkner], n.d., 1 item. (Oversize OS Box T-25.)
  - School Programs and Honors for Jill Faulkner, 1941-1953, 7 items. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Star-Spangled Banner Stuff, story by Estelle Oldham Faulkner, n.d., TMs. (Box-folder 6:5)
    With autograph revisions, 65 pages (copy).
  - Writings by Estelle Oldham Faulkner, n.d., 5 items. (Box-folder 6:6)
    Includes poems Lament of a Purist and Madison Avenue Blues and essay Dear Silent Unity.
  - Writings- Family: A Hunter's Branch, story by Paul D. Summers, 1962, n.d., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:7)
    With autograph revisions by William Faulkner; A Christmas in Columbus, an excerpt from his book of reminiscences of his stepfather, William Faulkner, by Malcolm A. Franklin, 6 pages.
  - Writings- Miscellaneous: The Quarrelsome King, story by Mrs. Phil Stone; A Latin-American Publishing House of Technical Texts, speech by Enrique Auvert, 1939, 1959, 5 items. (Box-folder 6:8)
- Series VI: Bound Volumes and Audio Recordings
  - Subseries A: Bound Volumes
    - Daybook, kept by William Faulkner, 1938-1943 (Box-folder 6:9)
    - Daybook, kept by William Faulkner, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 6:10)
    - Daybook, kept by William Faulkner, 1942-1959 (Box-folder 6:11)
    - Flight Log/Engine Log, kept by William Faulkner, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 6:12)
    - Ledger, kept by William Faulkner, 1949-1955 (Box-folder 6:13)
    - Ledger, kept by William Faulkner, 1955-1960 (Box-folder 6:14)
    - Miscellaneous: grocery lists, notes, etc., 1942-1946 (Box-folder 6:15)
    - Pilots Log, kept by William Faulkner, 1933-1942 (Box-folder 6:16)
    - Record of Horse Breeding, kept by William Faulkner, 1938-1942 (Box-folder 6:17)
    - Exhibition of Paintings by Estelle Oldham Faulkner, 1964, 1964 (Box-folder 6:18)
      Contains an exhibit catalog and invitation for the opening of the exhibit, copies of some of the pieces, copy of the guest list, and copies of correspondence about the exhibit.
  - Subseries B: Audio Recordings
    - Faulkner SMMSS [Verchul Jones], ca. 1938, Home-disc recording, acetate-aluminum. 78 rpm.
    - University of Virginia News Conference on Faulkner, taped by WINA, Charlottesville, 1962 July 6
      With comments by Fredson Bowers, Floyd Stovall, James B. Colvert, F. W. Bernhauser, and John Cook Wyllie, ca. 30 minutes.
    - The Faulkner Story, The Ford Foundation, TV-Radio Workshop, n.d.
    - Faulkner 1st period, n.d.
    - Faulkner 2nd period, n.d.
    - [Faulkner ? ] n.d.